A Guide to the Papers of Lynchburg, Virginia Families, 1926
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Other Civil War letters to Deborah Anne Dudley include one, June 11, 1864, from Samuel K. Huys in Clinton, Louisiana during the Red River Campaign. Huys mentions troop movement to Red River, Louisiana from Abingdon, Virginia, describing the trip on horseback through rough and mountainous country to Atlanta, Georgia and through pine woods from Mobile, Alabama to Clinton, Louisiana. He refers to the lack of food for people throughout, the suffering of people in east Tennessee and in the mountains of North Carolina, and life in Clinton, describing the Red River, Louisiana area and mentioning the high incidence of widows.. He mentions his brother being in the prison camp at Point Lookout, Maryland; being in charge of the officer's hospital; and being pleasantly situated for now. He refers to his traveling party, including officers, servants, horses and wagons, and mentioning [Simon Bolivar] Buckner (1823-1914), R. A. Johnson, [Patrick Ronayne] Cleburne (1828-1864), and [Randall Lee] Gibson (1832-1892). He discusses activities of the Red River Campaign and the Trans-Mississippi. He mentions Colonel John Scott of the 1st Louisiana Cavalry being in charge of the district; the breakup of a Yankee plantation and the capture of sixty mules and some "Negroes"; the enemy entrenched camp at Morganza, Louisiana; General [Nathaniel Prentiss] Banks having lost over twenty thousand men, fourteen gunboats and some twenty transports; General [Frederick] Steele having lost some five thousand men and as much transportation; Steele last being seen in Little Rock, Arkansas pursued by [Sterling "Pap"] Price (1809-1867) and [John Sappington] Marmaduke (1833-1887); the impression that Steele will fall back to Missouri; opinions on the Army of General [Joseph Eggleston] Johnston and a diversion in the direction of St. Louis, Missouri and General [William Tecumseh] Sherman (1820-1891); General [Richard] "Dick" Taylor (1826-1879) being between General [Nathaniel Prentiss] Banks' Army and News Orleans, Louisiana; General [Edward Richard Sprigg] Canby (1817-1873) assuming Banks' command; and, sending greetings from [Simon Bolivar] Buckner.
There is a letter, October 10, 1865, to Deborah Anne Dudley on her wedding day, from Anne E. Johns in Leamington, England, discussing her marriage to William H. Kinckle and describing travel in England, including Leamington, Kenilworth, Warwick Castle, Oxford, and Blenheim. She discusses various places relating to Shakespeare, including Stratford-upon-Avon and the burial place of Shakespeare and Anne Hathaway. There is a letter, July 24, 1868, from John R. Lee of Martinsville, Henry County, Virginia, concerning the death of William H. Kinckle and including religious thought and advice of child-rearing.
There is miscellaneous correspondence, 1828-1913, and no date, relating to family news, social life, and other matters. A letter of September 23, 1828 from Nancy Davis to Peter Dudley elaborates on a visit to Lynchburg by Henry Clay. There is a letter, February 5, 1858, from [ ] Barrett in Richmond concerning political activity and an upcoming election. A letter, November 15, 1865, from Nannie McCorkle of Lynchburg concerns the organization of a Ladies Aid Society formed in order to provide aid to poor preachers by collecting provisions, clothes and money. There is a lengthy and expressively descriptive letter, March 20, 1866, from Anne E. Johns in Rome, Italy, concerning travel in London, England; Paris, France; and, Rome and Naples, Italy. The letter mentions the "Piazza di Spagna," the ruins, the Dome of St. Peter, the Roman Aqueduct, an omnibus accident, and a pickpocket attempt. There are three letters, 1895 and 1901, from "Wes" at Greenbrier, White Sulphur Springs, West Virginia and Arlington Stables, Washington, D. C., mentioning the fine potato crops, the livery stables at the spa, and social news. There is a (copy of a) letter to Franklin Owens mentioning the birth of his son, Benjamin Franklin Owens, Jr.; describing the St. Paul's (Episcopal Church) Fair in Lynchburg with a discussion of the goods sold; and, seeking assistance in the settlement of the estate of his [late wife] Jane's uncle, George Latham, of Savannah, Georgia.
There are also business and legal papers of the Adams, Davis, Johns, and related families. Among the legal papers of Stephen Adams are: Albany Academy certificates, 1843-1844; copy of his will, January 21, 1869, leaving his property to his wife Emma C. Adams; papers, 1903, concerning the claim of an invalid pension for Robert E. Mitchell who became ill during detached service to Yosemite Park; and, a "Report of Alumni Advisory Board to Yale Corporation on the Stimulation of Intellectual Activity among Undergraduates," June 20, 1910.
Among the Davis family business papers are accounts for whitewashing and plastering (September 11, 1827 & October 3, 1828), hat and hat repair (May 23, 1828), cart and wheelbarrow parts (September 1828), dental work (1854), [horse] shoe and shoe repair (February 15, n.y.), and sundry items. There is also a note regarding an allowance to a Mrs. Murphy by the Board of Overseers of the Poor (February 21, 1829), the settlement of partnership business of Davis & Byars (18[ ]8 March 25), a proposal from Elizabeth Thomas to wash, lodge and board for $1.50 per week (n.d.), an account for carpentry and building (n.d.).
Among the accounts of John Johns are purchases of various sewing materials and accessories, ladies shoes and boots, and clothing; accounts for smith work; and, receipts for payments for shares in the stock of the Office of the Virginia and Tennessee Railroad Company. Among the accounts of Thomas Johns are purchases for various foods and sundries. There are also accounts for work done on stables and kitchen by James W. Wright, including a list of hired hands (May 1865); smith work, listing specific items made, mended, repaired or removed, by Charles P. North (January 29, 1866); work on ambulance, wagon wheels, and wagon by John A. Roper (February 22, 1868); gold fillings (May 16, 1871); and, horseshoes (April 20, 1904). Thomas Johns also has tobacco accounts, 1880-1900, with Lynchburg commission merchants, Jacob H. Franklin and Company, Callahan and Franklin, Murrell, Fleming and Company, Green H. Nowlin, and Walter S. Fore and Company. Legal papers of Thomas Johns relate to the sale of tracts of land in Campbell County (June 19, 1856 and February 1, 1871); the milling business (December 3, 1870 and December 21, 1877); and agreements to cultivate land (October 17, 1872 and September 14, 1878). Among the receipts of Thomas Johns is a receipt, January 12, 1858, from D. P. and G. Diuguid "For Burial of Black Man 8.00." There are also tax receipts for Campbell County and Appomattox County to Thomas Johns. Miscellaneous business and legal papers include a summons to the proprietors of Friends Warehouse in Lynchburg (September 1850); a certification that Reverend William H. Kinckle has taken the Oath prescribed by the President in his proclamation of December 8, 1863; and, a statement of tobacco sold at Friends Warehouse (September 30, 1889).
There is genealogical data on the Davis, Dudley and Payne families and historical data on Lynchburg. The social items include a marriage invitation for Grace Dudley Kinckle and William Saunders Adams (December 23, 1890) and a souvenir menu and ribbon from the Columbian Naval Parade Steamer Howard Carrol. Among the writings are a diary entry, September 1849, of religious thoughts and activities [kept by Deborah Ann Dudley], religious essays, a tribute to John Kirkpatrick, and an address to the Ladies of the Memorial Association (pages 1 and 2 missing). There is an autograph book of Yale College graduates kept by Stephen Adams which include comments by Denison Olmsted (1791-1859), Noah Porter (1811-1892), Thomas A[nthony] Thacher (1815-1886), James Hadley (1821-1872), Nathaniel Shipman (1828- 1906), William R[oot] Bliss (1825- 1906), Martin Kellogg (1828-1903), and Ellis H[enry] Roberts (1827-1918). The diary and commonplace book, 1900-1901, of Grace Kinckle Adams contains entries concerning her daily life, family and friends, and, especially, her parents, Grace Dudley (Kinckle) and William Saunders Adams. The scrapbook, 1881-1898, kept by Stephen Adams includes newspaper clippings of editorial correspondence, 1881, during a trip to Rotterdam, Amsterdam, Cologne, Wiesbaden, Antwerp, Brussels, Paris, and London; on various historical and political figures; on a great fire in Lynchburg in 1883; and, of poetry. There is also an extract from the oration, "Biographical Sketch of General Robert E. Lee," by John W. Daniel at the unveiling of the Lee statue (June 28, 1883).
Contents List
- Correspondence
  - Andalusia (Fourquerean) Dudley 1851, 1887, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Henry Dudley 1849-1857, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Peter Lewis Dudley 1851-1854 (Box 1)
  - Robert Leslie Dudley 1846-1864 (Box 1)
  - Mary Elizabeth (Dudley) and Thomas W. Johns 1880-1899 (Box 1)
  - William G. Luck 1864-1865 (Box 1)
  - James F. Payne 1849-1960 (Box 1)
  - Robinson C. Pierce 1862-1865 (Box 1)
  - G. K. Turner 1863-1864 (Box 1)
  - Letters to Deborah Anne Dudley 1852-1871, 1907, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Letters 1828-1913, n.d., 2 folders (Box 1)
- Business Papers
  - Stephen Adams: Legal Papers 1843-1910 (Box 1)
  - William Davis: Account Book 1814-1821 (Box 1)
  - Davis Family: Business Papers 1774-1860, n.d., 2 folders (Box 1)
  - John Johns: Business Papers 1820-1865 (Box 1)
  - Thomas W. Johns: Accounts 1837-1904, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Thomas W. Johns: Accounts for Tobacco 1880-1900 (Box 1)
  - Thomas W. Johns: Legal Papers 1856-1879 (Box 1)
  - Thomas W. Johns: Receipts 1848-1903 (Box 1)
  - Thomas W. Johns: Tax Receipts 1852-1888 (Box 1)
  - Johns Family: Business Papers 1879-1904 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Business Papers 1818-1909 (Box 1)
- Topical
  - Genealogical and Historical Data 1890-1957, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Poetry 1845, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Social 1853-1892 (Box 2)
  - Writings 1904, n.d. (Box 2)
  - (Box 2)
- Bound Volumes
  - Autograph Book of Yale Graduates kept by Stephen Adams 1850 (Box 2)
  - Class Notes for Senior Regular Law kept by John L. Adams 1882 (Box 2)
  - Commonplace Book kept by Grace Dudley Kinckle 1876 (Box 2)
  - Diary and Commonplace Book kept by Grace Kinckle Adams 1900-1901 (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook kept by Stephen Adams 1881-1898 (Box 2)